<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>Mephibosheths hearts-ioy vpon his soueraignes safetie To be imitated by the subjects of this land vpon the happy returne of our Prince Charles. Deliuered in a sermon in the church of Great Yarmouth in Norfolke, the 19. day of October. 1623. By Tho: Reeue preacher of Gods word there.</title>
            <author>Reeve, Tho. (Thomas), 1583 or 4-1651.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1624</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 66 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 24 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2011-12">2011-12 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A10562</idno>
            <idno type="STC">STC 20832A</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC S103452</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">99839205</idno>
            <idno type="PROQUEST">99839205</idno>
            <idno type="VID">3607</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A10562)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 3607)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1475-1640 ; 1253:21)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>Mephibosheths hearts-ioy vpon his soueraignes safetie To be imitated by the subjects of this land vpon the happy returne of our Prince Charles. Deliuered in a sermon in the church of Great Yarmouth in Norfolke, the 19. day of October. 1623. By Tho: Reeue preacher of Gods word there.</title>
                  <author>Reeve, Tho. (Thomas), 1583 or 4-1651.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[4], 42 p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>Printed by Aug: Math[ewes]: for Robert Milbourne and are to be sold at his shop at the great south doore of Saint Paules,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>London :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1624.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Printer's name from STC.</note>
                  <note>Some print faded and show-through, and some pages stained.</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of original in the Union Theological Seminary.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Charles --  I, --  King of England, 1600-1649 --  Sermons --  Early works to 1800.</term>
               <term>Sermons, English --  17th century.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2011-02</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-02</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-04</date>
            <label>Ali Jakobson</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-04</date>
            <label>Ali Jakobson</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-06</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:3607:1" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:3607:1"/>
            <p>
               <hi>Mephiboſheths</hi> HEARTS-IOY Vpon his SOVERAIGNES SAFETIE.</p>
            <p>To be imitated by the Sub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jects of this Land vpon the hap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>py Returne of our Prince CHARLES.</p>
            <p>Deliuered in a Sermon in the Church of Great <hi>Yarmouth</hi> in Norfolke, the 19. day of <hi>October.</hi> 1623.</p>
            <p>By THO: REEVE Preacher of Gods Word there.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>LONDON</hi> Printed by <hi>Aug: Math:</hi> for <hi>Robert Milbourne</hi> and are to be ſold at his Shop at the great South doore of Saint <hi>Paules.</hi> 1624.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="dedication">
            <pb facs="tcp:3607:2"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:3607:2"/>
            <p>TO THE RIGHT WORSHIPFVLL THOMAS THOMSON and LEONARD HOAMES Bailiffes of Great <hi>Yarmouth.</hi> AND TO THE ALDER<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>men and the reſt of the <hi>Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mons, of that worthy</hi> INCORPO<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>RATION.</p>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="sermon">
            <pb facs="tcp:3607:3"/>
            <pb n="1" facs="tcp:3607:3"/>
            <head>MEPHIBOSETH'S Hearts-Ioy vpon his So<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ueraignes Safetie.</head>
            <epigraph>
               <bibl>Text. <hi>2 SAM. 19.30.</hi>
               </bibl>
               <q>Yea let him take all, ſeeing my Lord the King is come home in Peace.</q>
            </epigraph>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">O</seg>H how ioyfull was the ſafetie of Iſraels Worthy! <hi>Dauids</hi> danger being great, his deli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uery gracious, <hi>En quanta ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ultatio, quanta congratulatio!</hi> Behold how great exultation, how great congratulation was there for it! His Subiects come to behold him like the <hi>Dar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ling</hi> of <hi>Heauen,</hi> the <hi>Delight</hi> of the <hi>Earth;</hi> for where the <hi>Finger of God</hi> had wrought ſo won<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derfull a Preſeruation, oh how are the peoples hearts ſet on fire to come and admire it! their feete are like <hi>Hindes feet</hi> to ſet forward vnto
<pb n="2" facs="tcp:3607:4"/>
it, and their eyes are like the Lions, but halfe-ſleeping, till they haue enioyed a ſight of it. What is our King paſt this perill? Is <hi>Dauid</hi> that was giuen ouer for dead yet aliue? <hi>Cur in Tentorijs?</hi> Why ſtay we ſtill in our Tents? Let vs out, and ſalute him, that ſo wee may make the world to ring with our Ioy, and the Skye to reſound with our gladſome melody, ſinging in ſongs, and warbling foorth with the lowdeſt, loftieſt ſtreynes. <hi>En Gaudium Cordium Oculis Reuiſum! En Gloriam Iſraelis, Gloria ſpirantem! En Regem A Rege Regum Protectum!</hi> Behold the Ioy of our Hearts re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>turned to the ſight of our Eyes! Behold the Glory of Iſrael breathing yet in Glory! Be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hold our King by the King of Kings prote<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cted! For this end yee may ſee the <hi>GRAN<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>DIES, Peeres,</hi> and all ſorts of People iſſuing foorth, <hi>Vt Apes<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> Praeſepibus,</hi> like a ſwarme of Bees out of their Hiues, to ſee and ſolemnize ſo miraculous and memorable an accident. Iſrael ſpurring on one another why they ſhould be <hi>ſo</hi>
               <note n="a" place="margin">Verſe 10</note> 
               <hi>ſlow;</hi>
               <note n="b" place="margin">Verſe 15</note> Iudah comming downe to Gil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gall <hi>to meet the King and conduct him ouer</hi> Ior<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dan. Nay not ſo much but that <hi>dead Dogge Shimei</hi> that before had rayled and reuiled vp<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on <hi>Dauid</hi> and caſt ſtones<note n="c" place="margin">Verſe 16</note> 
               <hi>haſted, and came downe;</hi> yea and as if he had thought it vnfiting to come alone, he gathers vp the people of the Countrey, and appeares
<q>Magna ſtipante caterua</q>
               <pb n="3" facs="tcp:3607:4"/>
With a great traine at his heeles, for hee brought <hi>a</hi>
               <note n="d" place="margin">Verſe 17</note> 
               <hi>Thouſand men of Beniamin with him.</hi> And is heere all? No, <hi>Zibah</hi> ſeruant of <hi>the Houſe of Saul</hi> is there with no ſmall reti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>new, but hath his<note n="e" place="margin">Verſe 17</note> 
               <hi>fifteene Sonnes, and twenty ſeruants with him:</hi> Nay, behold a man ready to goe dwell with the Wormes, creeping forth to ſee this ſight, one that was <hi>capularis ſenex,</hi> a man as mellow for the Graue, as the Summer Apple for the Pomary, which for very pure Age had <hi>neither</hi>
               <note n="f" place="margin">Verſe 3<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>
               </note> 
               <hi>taſte of his meate, and drinke, nor could heare the voyce of Singing men and Sing<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing women,</hi> yet he cannot keepe in; for<note n="g" place="margin">Verſe <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>
               </note> 
               <hi>Bar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>zillai the Gileadite came downe from Rogelim, and went ouer Jordan with the King, to conduct him ouer Iordan.</hi> Oh gratious <hi>DELIVE<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>RANCE</hi> magnificently ſelebrated! Oh <hi>HAPPY FAVOVR</hi> of <hi>GOD</hi> ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>companied with <hi>WORTHY OBSER<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>VANCE</hi> from men! Oh but amongſt all theſe loyall Subiects full of ſuch ardent expreſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſions of Ioy. <hi>
                  <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>bi MEPHIBOSHETH filius Jonathae? Where is MEPHIBO<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>SHETH the Sonne of Ionathan?</hi> What doth he not remember the ancient loue and ſtrict couenant that was betweene his Father <hi>Iona<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>than</hi> and <hi>Dauid?</hi>
               <note n="h" place="margin">2 Sam 17.</note> 
               <hi>Ionathan loued Dauid as his owne Soule,</hi> and a vowe was made that there ſhould be firme loue<note n="i" place="margin">1 Sam 42.</note> betweene them and their ſeed for euer, and when <hi>Jonathan</hi> was dead <hi>Da<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uid</hi> wept and mourned for him,<note n="k" place="margin">2 Sam 26.</note> 
               <hi>Woe is me for
<pb n="4" facs="tcp:3607:5"/>
thee my brother Ionathan: very kinde haſt thou been to me, thy loue to mee was wonderfull, paſsing the loue of women.</hi> How are the <hi>mighty ouer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>throwne, and the weapons of Warre deſtroyed?</hi> Now then, <hi>
                  <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>bi MEPHIBOSHETH filius Jonathae? Where is MEPHIBOSHETH the Sonne of Jonathan?</hi>
               <note place="margin">Prouerb.</note> 
               <hi>Thy Fathers friend ſhalt thou not forſake,</hi> ſaith <hi>Salomon.</hi> But what are all ſparkes of olde loue extinct? Are all kind<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly affections periſhed? Are there no remnants of the former amitie and vnitie? <hi>
                  <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>bi ME<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>PHIBOSHETH filius Ionathae? Where is MEPHIBOSHETH the Sonne of Jona<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>than? Quid cogitas? Quid moliris?</hi> What plots, and deuiſes haſt thou in thy head? What art thou caſting about for the Kingdome? So <hi>Zi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bah</hi> indeed inform that <hi>MEPHIBOSHETH</hi> ſtayed at Ieruſalem, hoping that the<note n="m" place="margin">2 Sam. 3.</note> 
               <hi>Houſe of Iſrael would reſtore to him the Kingdome of his Father:</hi> but they were but <hi>in blandae menda<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cia linguae,</hi> the whiſperings of a falſe tongue. <hi>Zibah</hi> played the Foxe-part; for <hi>MEPHI<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>BOS:</hi> was an honeſt man, and here is found in the middſt of this Chapter full of the com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mendableſt devoyre, as the Sonne is in the middſt of the Planets full of Radiant ſplendor: Now becauſe <hi>MEPHIBOSHETH</hi> is the party vpon whom I muſt fixe my chiefe diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>courſe; Let vs make his Deſcription in this Chapter as the entrance to the reſt, as <hi>Salo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mons Temple</hi> had a <hi>Beautifull Gate</hi> before the going in.</p>
            <p>
               <pb n="5" facs="tcp:3607:5"/>Three things are remarkeable in him.</p>
            <p>Firſt, His mournefull behauiour till the <label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">Note. </seg>1</label> Kings returne; for<note n="n" place="margin">Verſe 24<g ref="char:punc">▪</g>
               </note> 
               <hi>He had neither waſhed his feet, nor dreſſed his beard, nor waſhed his cloathes, from the time that the King departed vntill hee re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>turned in peace.</hi> Oh rare ſpectacle of prime fi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>delitie! What is he elſe but a <hi>MIRROVR</hi> of a <hi>True-hearted Subiect?</hi> How could a man expreſſe more paſsionate reſpect vnto his Prince?</p>
            <p>Secondly, His innocencie from the leaſt <label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">Note. </seg>2</label> taint of that calumny, and reproach, that was craftily and maliciouſly caſt vpon him by <hi>Zi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bah;</hi> For, he ſtay at Ieruſalem for the reuolu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of the Scepter vnto <hi>Sauls</hi> ſtock in his per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon? No, <hi>Abſit,</hi> Farre be it from him, his innocent heart neuer harboured ſuch a wretch<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed thought. There was laid to his charge a thing that he knew not; for he counted him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelfe bound for euer to <hi>Dauid</hi> for his life, and meanes, that out of mercie hee had vouchſafed vnto him: For<note n="o" place="margin">Verſe 2</note> 
               <hi>All my Fathers houſe were but dead men before my Lord the King, yet didſt thou ſet thy Seruant among them, that did eate at thine owne Table. Siccine igitur rependam?</hi> What therefore for ſuch gracious fauours ſhall I re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>turne ſuch blacke requitall? No, if it pleaſe the King to vnderſtand the truth, there was one went betweene me and home, that Sycophant <hi>Zibah</hi> dealt perfidiouſly, and fraudulently with me, for I ſpake to him (being my ſeruant) <hi>to
<pb n="6" facs="tcp:3607:6"/>
ſaddle mine Aſſe that I</hi> might at the firſt haue gone with thee,<note place="margin">Verſe 26</note> and drunke of the ſame cuppe, but he went and tooke the beaſt for himſelfe, and left mee at home, through lameneſſe, not being able to follow; and thus what with his preſents, and glozing ſpeeches hath hee rayſed vp an euill report againſt me; But, oh King, thou haſt wiſdome enough to ſee his ſubdo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>louſneſſe, my vprightneſſe; to thee therefore doe I referre it,<note n="p" place="margin">Verſe 27</note> 
               <hi>My Lord the King is as an Angell of God, doe therefore thy pleaſure.</hi> Thus <hi>MEPHIBOSHETH</hi> aſſoyle and acquit him ſelfe from the imputation of that bitter ſlan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der, ſhewing that he ſtayed not at Ieruſalem to ſtirre vp ſedition, nor vpon this occaſion of <hi>Dauids</hi> troubles to worke his owne endes, and aduantages, but was conſtrayned there to re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>maine, and all the while of the Kings abſence continued a peaceable and well-wiſhing Sub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>iect.</p>
            <p>Thirdly, His generous anſwere vpon <hi>Da<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uids</hi> too too moderate ſatisfaction; for be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore vpon <hi>Zibahs</hi> ſmooth tale <hi>Dauid</hi> had giuen away all <hi>MEPHIBOSHTHS</hi> Lands to <hi>Zi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bah,</hi>
               <note n="q" place="margin">
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> Sam. 16</note> 
               <hi>Behold, thine are all that pertained to MEPHIBOSHETH.</hi> But now perceiuing <hi>MEPHIBOSHETH</hi> to be guiltleſſe hee thought it vnmeet, vnreaſonable, but that ſome reſtitution ſhould be made him, therefore ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>iudge hee,<note n="r" place="margin">
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>erſe 29</note> 
               <hi>Thou and Zibah deuide the Lands:</hi> Now though <hi>Zibah</hi> deſerued rather to haue
<pb n="7" facs="tcp:3607:6"/>
bene diuided in pieces, then to haue any diui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion of the Lands; yet, doth <hi>MEPHIBO<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>SHETH</hi> carry himſelfe diſcontentedly? No, <hi>Non frendet, non labrum mordet;</hi> He ſhewes no token of diſlike, for ſee his notable demeanour, nay, heare his reſolute and Laudable anſwere. It is not my goods, ſaith he, that I care for, but the Kings life, and therefore (that I may ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>peare to be what I plead for, a well affectionate ſubiect) <hi>My Lord the King being come home in Peace,</hi> I am ſo ouerioyed with it, that I reſpect no wordly wealth, and that I may manifeſt it, I ſubmit my ſelfe to thy determination, that <hi>Zibah</hi> ſhould haue halfe my meanes, nay, that he ſhould poſſeſſe the whole portion. <hi>Yea</hi> (ſaith good <hi>MEPHIBOSHETH) Let him take all, ſeeing my Lord the King is come home in Peace.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>This Alablaſter Boxe of <hi>MEPHIBO<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>SHETHS</hi> matchleſſe anſwere doe I pur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſe to open amongſt you, and to powre out the precious Spiknard in the ſame, that the whole houſe may bee filled with the ſauour of it, and all of vs incited to ſome ſemblable ioy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fulneſſe vpon the happy returne of our <hi>Illuſtri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous Prince.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>In the words there are two parts.
<list>
                  <item>A wonderfull tranſporting.</item>
                  <item>A cauſe of weight importing.</item>
               </list>
            </p>
            <list>
               <pb n="8" facs="tcp:3607:7"/>
               <item>1 The wonderfull tranſporting, <hi>Yea let him take All.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>2 The cauſe of weight importing, <hi>Seeing my Lord the King is come home in Peace.</hi>
               </item>
            </list>
            <p>Firſt, for the wonderfull Tranſporting, <hi>Yea let him take All.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>This Tranſporting ſeemes to be wonderfull for three reſpects, of
<list>
                  <item>The Perſon Him, <hi>Yea let him</hi>
                  </item>
                  <item>The Proffer Take, <hi>Yea let him take</hi>
                  </item>
                  <item>The Portion All, <hi>Yea, &amp;c.</hi>
                  </item>
               </list>
            </p>
            <p>Firſt, for the tranſporting as it ſeeme won<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derfull in reſpect of the Perſon. <hi>Him. Let him, Zibah.</hi> Had it beene ſome ancient friend, or entire approued acquaintance, it had beene leſſe maruellous, but <hi>Let Him.</hi> What the trea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cherouſeſt Miſcreant that euer <hi>MEPHIBO<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>SHETH</hi> had againſt him? He that had bru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed his heele, empeached his credit, that dead flye that had made the ſweet oyntment of his fame to ſtincke? That faithleſſe wretch who being one of his owne Houſhold, had layd a wound vnd<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>r his ſide? What Let him? Yes, <hi>Let Him,</hi> ſaith <hi>MEPHIBOSHETH:</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <note place="margin">Obſerue.</note>Oh, what ſee we here but a heart offended, relenting, and inclining to peace? Was hee euer grieued againſt <hi>Zibah?</hi> Were it ſo, yet <hi>Neſcit odiſſe,</hi> he knowes not how to hate: as <hi>Dauid</hi> will keepe his eyes from looking vpon
<pb n="9" facs="tcp:3607:7"/>
vanity; ſo <hi>Mephiboſheth</hi> his heart from mu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>zing vpon vengeance: He will poure coales of fire vpon his Enemies head for, <hi>Let Him.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>How choiſe and conſpicuous is this Paterne? How many amongſt vs can thus hide reproofes in our boſomes? and when our cheekes are nipped, our faces ſmitten, long furrowes made vpon our backes, not feele the ſmart of the ſame? No, it was a true ſpeech of<note n="ſ" place="margin">Laert. lib. <hi>5.</hi> cap. <hi>1.</hi>
               </note> 
               <hi>Ariſtotle</hi> who being demanded, what was the firſt, and what was the laſt thing that waxed olde, an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwered, <hi>Gratia &amp; Jniuria:</hi> a good turne firſt, a bab turne laſt: becauſe of kindneſſes we are ſo ſoone forgetfull, but of vnkindneſſe, <hi>valdè tenaces</hi> ſuch long remembrancers.<note n="t" place="margin">Prou. 19.11.</note> 
               <hi>The glory of a man is to paſſe by an offence,</hi> but this glory is eſteemed of many the greateſt ignominy: for, what forget an indignitie, bury a gree<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uance, oh this were a Daſtardly thing indeede? no, wreacke our teene, feede our eyes with the ruine of our Aduerſaries, this is manly, this is glorious:
<q>— ſcribunt in marmore laeſi.</q>
The duſt is no fit Regiſter for wrongs, but they write them in Tables of Marble, and til they ſee due repaiment there is no true con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tent; an eye for an eye, and a tooth for a tooth, we are rather <hi>Eſaus</hi> then <hi>Mephiboſheths:</hi> As it is reported of<note n="u" place="margin">Herod. lib. <hi>5.</hi>
               </note> 
               <hi>Darius</hi> that hauing recei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ued an abuſe from the <hi>Athenians,</hi> he ſhot vp an arrow into Heauen, and fell into an ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>treame
<pb n="10" facs="tcp:3607:8"/>
rage, withall commanding one of his ſeruants that euery Supper time he ſhould ſay, <hi>Here memento Athenienſium, Maſter remember the Athenians.</hi> So fares it with vs vpon the leaſt ill turne, wee fall into furious behauiour, and vſe all meanes whereby the memorie of ſuch things might remaine freſh with vs con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tinually. But oh in the meane while where is the power of diuine grace? Haue wee ſo lear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned <hi>Chriſt?</hi> Is this the light that Gods bleſſed truth inſtructeth vs in? No, The<note n="w" place="margin">Iam. 3.17</note> 
               <hi>Wiſdome that deſcend from aboue is peaceable, eaſie to bee intreated.</hi>
               <note n="x" place="margin">Prou. 24.29.</note> 
               <hi>Say not, I will doe to him as he hath done to me, I will recompence euery man according to his workes.</hi>
               <note n="y" place="margin">Rom. 12.2</note> 
               <hi>Be not ouercome with euill, but ouercome euill with goodneſſe.</hi> Away then with thoſe vindictiue and implacable Spirits, which boile with nothing but rancour, and thirſt af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter the ouerthrowe of their foes, and aduerſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ries. Oh let Aſpes haue theſe galles, but in the boſomes of Saints let them neuer bee found! Amongſt vs let there be rather <hi>Jndolentia</hi> then <hi>Jnuidia,</hi> yea ſo tractable and flexible let vs ſeeme to be to our deadlieſt enemies, that wee be ready rather to benefit them, then infeſt and miſchiefe them. See here a renowned exam<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple, <hi>Zibah</hi> had groſſely, deepely, baſely abuſed <hi>Mephiboſheth;</hi> yet ſee his ſweet nature, to this man will he be courteous, For, <hi>Let him take all.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Now let vs come to the <hi>Proffer. Take.</hi> Had
<pb n="11" facs="tcp:3607:8"/>
it beene let him enioy a gracious looke, or a good word it had beene much; but let him <hi>Take,</hi> what ſee wee heere but a moſt faire <hi>Proffer?</hi>
               <note place="margin">Obſerue.</note> Would <hi>Mephiboſheth</hi> thus to his ene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>my part with ſome of his Eſtate rather then ſtand, after <hi>Dauids</hi> iudgement giuen, conten<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding? Oh, might not this ſerue to charme our weariſomleſſe <hi>Law-wormes,</hi> which are giuen to interminable Suits, and many of them not (as <hi>Mephiboſheth</hi> might haue ſtood out heere for) due right, but for ſuch Poſſeſſions as haue beene tyrannouſly gotten, and are violently kept. How many of theſe are there whom no Iudges mouth can ſatisfie, nor Iuries equally choſen, and impartially dealing can bring to a ceſſation of their troubleſome Courſes? No, there are ſuch, which of their Rights are ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uer reſolued till their eſtates begin to bee diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſolued; the Lions cannot indure to part with ſpoyles gotten once into their iawes: for let euidence and oath declare neuer ſo cleerely; yet they ſee nothing, they yeeld nothing, but bend themſelues to another pleading, another tryall: many there are that haue theſe grie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uous Vexators continually moleſting them, as the Poets feigne <hi>Prometheus</hi> had a Vulture continually gnawing at his heart, whoſe lengthened Suites are as famous as <hi>Bellum De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>commale Troiae,</hi> as the tenne yeares Siege of Troy. Yee may know by ſome Sergeants and Councellours fat cheekes, if there be not ſuch
<pb n="12" facs="tcp:3607:9"/>
a peſtilent breed; for who know not theſe are the Pleaders good Benefactors? Let a Lawyer bee neuer ſo poore at the firſt; yet, if hee can but happen vpon ſuch a Booty, a wilfull Rich<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ling, the leane Kine will ſoone eate vp the fat; the Offerings of <hi>Moloch</hi> at the ſeuen <hi>Aumbries</hi> were neuer more coſtly and chargeable, (ſaue that of the liuing Child) then the Lawyers Ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lations; as <hi>Pharoah</hi> made the Iſraelites gather ſtraw, and make bricke for him; ſo theſe make their Clyents to gather and ſpare, racke, rend &amp; teare to diſcharge their Writs and Fees. I ſpeake the truth in the Lord, I lye not. Yet let the expences be neuer ſo great, where there are great Spirits, men will not bee daunted; ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny there are that had rather ſpend halfe of their meanes vpon ſuch, then to part with a quarter to make reſtitution for their il-gotten goods: and whereas God hath giuen men wealth to maintaine good Neighbourhood, and to liue comfortably in their owne Fami<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lies, rather then theſe men will ſatisfie what conſcience requireth, if either their owne power or their Councellors wit can withold it; let Hoſpitality be neglected, and the whole family eat the bread of carefulneſſe.</p>
            <q>Oh curuae in terris animae &amp; coeleſtium inanes.</q>
            <p>But for theſe endleſſe contentions, are not the Pleaders as deep in the guilt, as the gaines? Yes. Who know not that many of them when
<pb n="13" facs="tcp:3607:9"/>
they ſee the cauſe neuer ſo cleere againſt their Clients, and in Conſcience they ought to wiſh them to ſtirre no further, but to let the honeſt man haue his due; yet ſeeing hope of profit comming, they tell them this <hi>Demurre</hi> may be made, and that <hi>Quirke of Law</hi> pleaded, which fuell being adminiſtred, a great flame ſoone breakes foorth: therefore as a Pardall meete with a Lion to beget a Leopard; ſo the Plea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ders conioyne with their Clyents to breede vniuſt weariſom Sutes; when the Clients are at their wits end, and their ſpirits waxe blunt (for want of knowledge of any further ſcruple to be found and ſtood vpon) to proſecute fur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther quarrell, they goe to theſe as the<note n="z" place="margin">1 Sam. 13 20.</note> Iſrae<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lites went to the Philiſtimes <hi>to ſharpen their Mattockes and their Axes:</hi> and is it not much for theſe to diſanimate Clients deſirous of con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tention? Yes, it is as hard for Lawyers not to incite men to Sute, as it is for Panders not to entice men to vncleanneſſe, they know what will come of it, <q>Incidit in Scyllam qui vult vitare Charybdin.</q>
            </p>
            <p>Hee that will eſchew in this kinde an euill conſcience, there will be ſmall cuſtome, little commings in, hee muſt walke in a thried-bare gowne, and courſe vp at Termes without bux<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ome Attendants, and this Lawyers feauer com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>monly worſe then the clawes of Belzebub. All
<pb n="14" facs="tcp:3607:10"/>
this while I truſt I am not runne into <hi>Scanda<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lum Magnatum,</hi> but haue onely endeauoured to break <hi>Capita Draconum:</hi> I thought it conſci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ence, meeting them thus rightly, to ſmite them friendly, it may be a meanes to do them more good then to breake their heads with precious balmes, and to iuſtifie their abominable cour<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſes with the<note n="a" place="margin">Eccl. 7.7.</note> 
               <hi>Songs of Fooles,</hi> as <hi>Salomon</hi> calles flattering ſpeeches in a bad cauſe.</p>
            <p>Thus yee ſee how I haue reproued the inde<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fatigable Contender, and the heartening Plea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der, and can there in this any iniurie be done to either?<note place="margin">Horat.</note> No, <hi>Arcades ambo</hi>— both of them deſerue the blacke Coale.</p>
            <p>Well if this Fire can kindle it may be a means whereby there ſhall be no long variances, but quicke agreements, though it bee with loſſe; like to the courſe of <hi>Mephiboſheth</hi> here, whom <hi>Dauid</hi> adiudged to diuid the Lands with <hi>Zi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bah;</hi> now he being of no proterne refractary diſpoſition, nor hauing no prompting <hi>Ploydon</hi> at his elbow to tell him hee might make more worke, and bring about againe, yeelded ſome<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing, as ye may ſee already, in this Proffer, for <hi>Accipiat, Let him Take.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>But now let vs come further, and conſider the Portion. <hi>All. Let him take All.</hi> Not Halfe,<note place="margin">Obſerue.</note> but All: What ſee we heere but that in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>genuous people, good natures performe more then is required, whereſoeuer this vertue
<pb n="15" facs="tcp:3607:10"/>
ſhines, it is a kinde of a bright Image of God, for he vſe to giue more abundantly then wee can aske or craue. As <hi>Salomon</hi> deſired but wiſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dome of him, and not onely that is vouchſafed him, but<note n="b" place="margin">1 Kin. 3.13.</note> Alſo (ſaith the Lord) <hi>J haue giuen thee that which thou haſt not asked, both Riches and Honour, ſo that among the Kings there ſhall be none like vnto thee all the daies of thy life:</hi> and this good God good people deſire, endeauour to reſemble, as<note n="c" place="margin">Ruth. c 2.</note> 
               <hi>Booz</hi> when <hi>Ruth</hi> craued leaue <hi>to gleane in his Field,</hi> not onely granted what ſhe requeſted but added, that ſhe ſhould <hi>haue victuals and ſuſtenance with his Seruants:</hi> So<note n="d" place="margin">2 Sam. 24.</note> 
               <hi>Araunath</hi> when <hi>Dauid</hi> deſired but to buy the Threſhing-floor, yet he offered (though af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terwards <hi>Dauid</hi> would not accept any thing but vpon purchaſe) moſt freely, <hi>Let my Lord the King take and offer what ſeemeth him good in his eyes, behold the Oxen for the burnt offering and Chariots, and the inſtruments of the Oxen for wood, and it is ſaid, All theſe things did Arau<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nath as a King giue vnto the King.</hi> In like man<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ner<note n="e" place="margin">Neh 5.</note> 
               <hi>Nehemiah</hi> when the people complained that they were oppreſſed with the Vſury of their brethren, did not onely cauſe that to bee releaſed, but would not <hi>take the bread of the Go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uernour,</hi> and maintained a hundred and fiftie Iewes continually at his Table: ſo that ſo prompt are all well deuoted perſons that they exceede expectation; and are not their practi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſes anſwerable to Chriſts counſells? Yes,<note n="f" place="margin">Mat. 5.40.<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>1.</note> 
               <hi>If
<pb n="16" facs="tcp:3607:11"/>
any man will haue thy coate, let them take thy cloake alſo, and whoſoeuer will compell thee to goe with him a mile, goe twaine.</hi> How much are they to be blamed then, who are ſo farre from doing more then is deſired; that they are back<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ward to doe that which is meet and requiſite, which ſatisfie no lawfull deſires but ſlenderly and grudgingly; yea, with a repining, and cheereleſſe Spirit doe they ſtretch out their hand to any good dutie, &amp; were it not happily that ſhame may moue them, or authority force them, they would turne the All into Nothing. <hi>Nabal</hi> ſent <hi>Dauids</hi> meſſengers away with an emptie anſwere, and <hi>Diues</hi> will not vouchſafe to <hi>Lazarus</hi> ſo much as the crummes: and ſo indeed if many might haue their owne wills, litle it is that ſhould be giuen to Poore, Church or State, be the occaſions of demaunding neuer ſo forcing, the reaſons of requiring neuer ſo iuſt. But at laſt, let ſuch be aſhamed of their nigardizing, and endeauour to haue bowells enlarged, ſo that they may not onely fulfill, but exceede iuſt motions, let them not be too much ſet vpon the world like <hi>Mephiboſheth,</hi> there <hi>Let him take All.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Thus much for the wonderfull Tranſpor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting briefely handled, becauſe I aime not now ſo much at Explication, as Application.</p>
            <p>Let vs now come to the cauſe of weight Im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>porting, wherein there are three things like<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>wiſe
<pb n="17" facs="tcp:3607:11"/>
to be conſidered, The
<list>
                  <item>Man</item>
                  <item>Matter</item>
                  <item>Meaſure</item>
               </list> 
               <hi>The Lord the King is come home In Peace.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Firſt for the Man, <hi>Since my Lord the King.</hi> Was this the inducement that made him ſo free? no, ſome good thing that happened to his Lord the King. Then from hence obſerue,<note place="margin">Obſerue.</note> that both the Perſons, and bleſsings of Kings ought to be precious in the peoples eyes, and accounts: for if they be enriched with any ſin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gular fauour, this ought to be to them ſingu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lar Ioy. Oh whenſoeuer Heauens Power is gracious vnto them, they ſhould euen be rapt and rauiſhed with the ſame? For a rotten mem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ber is that that feele no comfort when the <hi>HEAD</hi> is annoynted with Balme, all ſhould ſeeme ſweetly to participate of the Superiours felicities.<note n="g" place="margin">2 Sam. 18 3.</note> 
               <hi>Thou art worth ten thouſand of vs,</hi> and therefore whatſoeuer beneficial thing ſuch enioy for glory and dignitie ſhould bee highly eſteemed of all them that belong to them. Oh wretched they therefore which haue little minde of their Lords their Kings, either con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cerning their perſons or bleſsings, they liue in a Common wealth, as in a houſe ouer which they remember no Maſter to be ſet; for let the diſtillations of Gods loue be neuer ſo plenti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full, it workes in them no admiration, no dele<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctation. But what are ſuch diuided branches?
<pb n="18" facs="tcp:3607:12"/>
If not, Why doe they not reioyce in the ſappe of their Roote? euery one ſhould ſtand bleſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſing of himſelfe in the happineſſe of his Soue<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>raigne, as we vſe to bleſſe our ſelues when wee behold the Sunne riſing in brightneſſe. Thus fared it with <hi>Mephiboſheth</hi> heere. <hi>Let him take all ſince my Lord the King.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>But is <hi>Dauid</hi> heere called <hi>Mephiboſheths</hi> Lord and King? Why ſo? for two reaſons.</p>
            <list>
               <item>1. For Defence.</item>
               <item>2. For Command.</item>
            </list>
            <p>Firſt, for Defence: For gracious Soue<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>raignes muſt bee the Peoples <hi>Lord-Protectors,</hi> by their power they muſt preſerue them in ſafety, as the <hi>Cherubims</hi> kept the way of the Tree of Life with the blade of a fiery ſword ſhaken. The Lord cryeth out againſt the<note n="h" place="margin">Zach. 11.17.</note> 
               <hi>Idol Shepheard</hi> that left the flock; ſo indeed a miſerable thing it is when the Prince hath no care of the welfare of his poore Subiects, they muſt carry their people in their boſomes, and<note n="i" place="margin">Numb. 11 12.</note> 
               <hi>as a Nurſe carryeth a ſucking Child;</hi> that is very regardfully and tenderly, ready to ſhel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter them from them that ſeeke to miſchiefe them, and to hold them vp in their Princely armes from falling into any dangers: It is not enough to bee knowne to be a Soueraigne as <hi>Auguſtus Caeſar</hi> was, by taxing his whole Dominions; but chiefly in ſafe garding the peoples Perſons and Eſtates.</p>
            <p>Secondly, they are Lords &amp; Kings for com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mand,
<pb n="19" facs="tcp:3607:12"/>
for what are they to bee vſed onely as walles of an Houſe to keepe out dangers, or as Flood-gates to keepe out Inundations, In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deed ſo many; too many carry themſelues vnto them, they are nimble to diſpute what a Soue<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>raigne ſtould doe; but they cannot hit of the veyne to conceiue what he ſhould haue, how he ſhould be reſpected, how reuerenced, how o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>beyed; for their honours are ſlightly giuen them, their commands coldly performed, their Tributes murmurringly paid, and all things wherein their Kingly Soueraignty conſiſts, faintly executed. Where is now then that of our Sauiour,<note n="k" place="margin">Math. 22.21.</note> 
               <hi>Giue vnto Caeſar that which is Caeſars;</hi> and that of the Apoſtle; <hi>Admone eos Principibus &amp; Poteſtaribus ſubditos eſſe,</hi>
               <note n="l" place="margin">Tit. 3.1.</note> 
               <hi>Put them in remembrance that they bee ſubiect to the Principalities and Powers.</hi> Famous is the com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mendations of <hi>Mutezumaes</hi> Subiects, who durſt not looke vpon his face for very reue<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rence, and if he did but ſend his Ring from his finger to the greateſt Commander vnder him (as it appeared in the diſmall Story of <hi>Qualpo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poca</hi> at the inſtigation of <hi>Cortez</hi>) in all the Do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>minions of the <hi>Mexicane</hi> Empire, though it coſt him his life, out of obedience he would not denye to come, and whatſoeuer by way of Tribure hee demanded, or by Edict publiſhed, all his people with the greateſt alacrity ſhew<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed their loyalty. Oh therefore, as we ought to pray vnto God that our Soueraignes with all
<pb n="20" facs="tcp:3607:13"/>
care, conſcience, compaſſion may defend vs: So wee ought to beſeech God to giue vs grace that in all ſubmiſſion and ſubiection we may obey them.</p>
            <p>But are the Lords and Kings for defence of vs and for command ouer vs? then who ſee not heere the neceſſity of Royall Authority? for, how ſhould wee euer bee in ſafety of our liues without their defence? and how would wee euer liue in any vertuous manner<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out their commands; take away the firſt, and wee are but like Sheepe without a Shepheard, ready to bee torne in pieces by euery beaſt of prey; take away the ſecond, and wee are but like wilde Aſſe-Colts, ſnuffing vp the wind at our pleaſure, prone to doe nothing but that which is good in our owne eyes: <hi>Siccine ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bet?</hi> goeth the matter thus? Let no man think then the Calling of Princes to be onely a mat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter of State and Pompe, where they might ſit in a Chayre of Magnificence, weare a Crown, ſhake a Scepter, but of vſe and worth.<note n="m" place="margin">Rom. 13.4.</note> 
               <hi>Hee is the Miniſter of God for thy good, Rom</hi> 1<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>.4. Let thoſe meane conceits therefore of the Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gall Office bee baniſhed, euer thinke highly of this Ordinance; for yee ſee it is not ſo much for Superiority and preheminence, as it is for vtility and emolument.</p>
            <p>Now let vs come to the matter, is <hi>Come home, Since my Lord the King is come home.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Quid deinde?</hi> What of that? Is that ſo
<pb n="21" facs="tcp:3607:13"/>
great a matter? Yes, with <hi>Mephiboſheth</hi> it was a motiue of great validity.<note place="margin">Obſerue.</note> From hence then who ſee not, that the abſence of Princes from their people, is a great darkening of their ioy? For, how can they miſſe them but with as great want as the want of the Sunne out of the Firmament? the Wife without her Husband hath no ſolace, nor the Kingdome without the King any true comfort; how can the Corner ſtone be taken from the building, and not great deformity? how can the chiefe ſtring bee wanting from the Inſtrument, and not faint Muſicke? So, how can there bee any hearty delight when the Lord the King is not in the midſt of the people?<note n="n" place="margin">1 Sam 9.</note> Did <hi>Saul</hi> thinke that if hee were wanting but three dayes, that his father would begin to ſorrow for him, and not much more the Subiects euen languiſh in themſelues when their Princes are in remote Parts:<note n="o" place="margin">Pſal. 82.</note> 
               <hi>I haue ſaid ye are Gods:</hi> Oh, how do the People reioyce in the preſence of their Gods, be it but to eye them, and behold ſuch royall Veſſels wherein the rich Treaſures of their bliſſe and happineſſe are ſtored vp. So that ſeeing the preſence of Princes is ſo great a comfort, <hi>Mephiboſheth</hi> heere you ſee had mat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter enough to bee wonderfully affected. For <hi>The Lord his King was come home.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Now let vs come to the meaſure, <hi>In peace: Seeing my Lord the King is come home in peace.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <pb n="22" facs="tcp:3607:14"/>This word peace I know hath many accep<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions; but if my iudgement faile mee not, for theſe three things it is heere put.</p>
            <p>Firſt, for freedome from former dangers; that wheras before <hi>Dauid</hi> was in great ſtraits, hee is now eſcaped out of them, Gods rod and ſtaffe hauing comforted him when hee was al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>moſt walking through the ſhadow of death, as the Iſraelites had many Egyptians purſuing after them, but when they looked backe they were all drowned: So, though this royal Prince had many feares &amp; terrors marching after him; yet now if hee looke backe, they are all ſwal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lowed vp, <hi>Dauid</hi> is now <hi>in peace.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Secondly, for health of body, That <hi>Dauid</hi> is not come home to lye on a Couch, or to bee wrung with ſome pangfull Diſeaſe, that hee needs not the Phiſitians to preſcribe recoue<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ring Receipts, but that hee finde his body in good temper, and himſelfe euery way health<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fully diſpoſed. <hi>Dauid</hi> is thus <hi>in peace.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Thirdly, for the good liking of his Subiects. That comming into his Territories hee is not enforced to take Caſtle, nor to enter into con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ditions of peace for the ſettling himſelfe in his Kingdome, but that all his Subiects as yet are well affected to him, and that <hi>Mephiboſheth</hi> ſee not a man that lifts vp his head, or threa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tens future moleſtation vnto him. <hi>Dauid is in peace.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>But is this the extent of <hi>Mephiboſheths</hi>
               <pb n="23" facs="tcp:3607:14"/>
weighty cauſe importing? is this that fill vp the Cup of his delight vnto the brimme? Then who ſee not that Subiects can neuer haue per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fection of comfort in their Princes, vnleſſe all their dangers bee remoued, if they bee not <hi>in peace,</hi> how ſtould the people bee in ioy? It is a prepoſtrous thing for the Subiects fore<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>heads to ſmile, when the Soueraignes forehead hangs downe; yet how many are there that can bee delightſome and mirthfull enough, in the midſt of their Rulers perils, and can tri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>umph in the midſt of their troubles? For my owne part, I thinke theſe know not what it is to haue a Superiour Power ouer them, for then the People with their Kings would like thoſe two famous Twinnes, weepe when they weep, and laugh when they laugh: <hi>Mephiboſheth</hi> I am ſure did ſo, all the while the King was in danger ye heard how diſconſolately hee beha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ued himſelfe, as though hee had beene a man careleſſe of himſelfe; and doth he expreſſe any ioy, when is it? when hee ſees his Lord the King in health and happineſſe, ſafety and ſecu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rity. For, <hi>Let him take all ſeeing my Lord the King is come home in Peace.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Thus at laſt haue I runne ſhort deſcant vpon the celebrious enſigne, notable carriage of <hi>Mephiboſheth.</hi> Oh <hi>Mephiboſheth,</hi> with re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nowne would I ſtill follow thee, I would I could blow a ſiluer Trumpet in thy praiſe, and ſet a Crowne of immortall honour vpon thy
<pb n="24" facs="tcp:3607:15"/>
Head. <hi>Floreat, ſplendeat ſemper Mephiboſheth.</hi> Let <hi>Mephiboſheths</hi> eſteeme euer flouriſh, euer flouriſh, and let it gliſter like <hi>Phoſphorus</hi> in his brightneſſe.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Quid vltra,</hi> What yet remaineth? To ſee whether wee haue ſuch ioyfull cauſe, that ſo wee may betake our ſelues to the like ioyfull carriage. Indeed to the Letter wee cannot hold; but wee can come as nigh to it as the Princely Eaglet come to the Kingly Eagle; for not <hi>the Lord our King is come home in peace,</hi> but <hi>the Lord our Prince is come home in peace:</hi> As for the Lord our King, hee being old ſtayed at home, in the middeſt of his Nobles, wearing the writhen, platted Crowne of Thornes in taking care for the welfare of his People, hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ring and anſwering forraigne Embaſſages, and conſulting how there might bee a ſpeedy con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cluding of the troubleſom affaires of Chriſten<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dome, and as his chiefeſt worke fitting him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelfe for his graue, and preparing his Soule for God. As for the Lord our Prince hee being yet young, and the Scepter being not yet in his hand, he vndertake hard Voyages, and be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing accompanied with ſome few Nobles (yea <hi>Ipſe vno graditur comitatus Achate</hi>) venters to ſee the faſhions of other Countries.<note place="margin">Virgil.</note> and the luſtres of other Courts. Well then, though the Lord our King went not forth, ſo that we might reioyce at his comming home, yet it was <hi>Filius Domini Regis, Adoleſcens ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cundus,
<pb n="25" facs="tcp:3607:15"/>
Spes Imperatoris, Jmperij,</hi> the neereſt to him in bloud, the deereſt vnto him in loue, the pleaſure of his eye, the ſtaſſe of his age, the ioy of his life, he for whom hee ſacrificed both morning and euening. So that vpon the perſon we need not much to ſtand.</p>
            <p>But what was the Lord our Prince in any great danger like <hi>Dauid?</hi> Yes, hee might ſay with <hi>Paul,</hi> that he was<note n="p" place="margin">2 Cor 11.</note> 
               <hi>Jn perills often, in perils by Land, in perils by Sea, in perils by Robbers, in perils in the Citie, in perils in the Wilderneſſe, in wearineſſe and painefulnes, &amp;c.</hi> Doubtleſſe ſo great were his dangers that there might haue bene but a hand-breath between him, &amp; death; and had not the Lord ſent his good Angel with him, as he did <hi>Raphael</hi> with <hi>Tobith</hi> hee might haue miſcaried betweene <hi>Niniueh</hi> and <hi>Rages.</hi> 1. For who know not that his paſſage ouer was troubleſome. 2. His ſpeedy iournying very weariſome. 3. His poſsibilitie of being diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>couered in a ſtrange Countrey, ſomething dan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gerous. 4. His ventring through Dales, For<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>reſts, ſolitary Plaines, hazardable. 5. His li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uing ſo long in a Kingdome (and that in the ſcorchingeſt time of Summer) not agreeable to his Nature, and when (as it is reported) a Plague ouerſpread the Land, perilous. 6. And at laſt (after his ſumptuous entertainment, and belike Magnificent welcome) hauing with honour and mutuall reſpects taken leaue of the Court of Spaine, entring into his Nauy (then
<pb n="26" facs="tcp:3607:16"/>
with what more vncertaine
<q>
                  <note place="margin">Horat.</note>Myrtoum pauidus nauta ſecat mare)</q>
by Windes, Tempeſts, Rockes, Sands, &amp;c. He might haue miſcaried, or wandred along while vpon the Seas, for
<q>
                  <note place="margin">Virgil.</note>Errabant acti fatis maria omnia circum,</q>
was it ſaid of the <hi>Trojans.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>But is there any ſuch ſad newes (at which our eares would haue tingled, our eyes drop<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ped out of our heads, our hearts broken within our boſomes, yea, we euen giuen vp the Ghoſt as <hi>Phineas</hi> wife did to heare that the Arke of the Lord was taken) to be at this time publi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhed amongſt vs? No: behold better newes, welcommer tidings, for to the ioy of the King, the delight of the Nobles, the comfort of the Clergy, the recreement of the whole Land, the <hi>Lord our Prince is come home in Peace.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="1">1 To the ioy of our King. For
<q>Omnis in Aſcanio chariſtat cura Parentis:</q>
no doubt al the Kings Care was ſetled vpon the ſafe returne of his <hi>Charles;</hi> yea, I doubt not much, whether (after he had ſent for him, and his Returne was determined) his Eyes tooke any quiet reſt, or the meat that he did eat were ſweet vnto him, or the light he did behold plea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſant, till it pleaſed God to grant him a ſight of him; as <hi>Dauid</hi> cryed, <hi>Oh my Sonne Abſolon, Abſolon, my Sonne, my Sonne, would to God I had dyed for thee.</hi> So, doubtleſſe, our King groaned within himſelfe, <hi>Oh my Sonne Charles, Charles
<pb n="27" facs="tcp:3607:16"/>
my Sonne, my Son, would to God I might ſet mine eye vpon thee.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="2">2 To the delight of the Nobles: For, muſt not they needs be ioyed to ſee the Mirrour of <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="2"/> Bloud and Progeny (vpon which they ſtand ſo much) and that rare Flowre of the Court pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſented againe before their eyes? Doubtleſſe, Yes: they cannot but bleſſe themſelues, to liue to that day to ſee their <hi>Lord their Prince, come home in Peace.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="3">3 To the comfort of the Clergy. The whole <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="3"/> Schoole of <hi>Shiloh</hi> reioyce in it; much mirth and melody is there at <hi>Naioth</hi> for it, yea euery Prieſt and Leuite is ready to ſing <hi>Hoſannah</hi> in the higheſt, to heare of it. Hee hath bene, is, and we hope euer will be our <hi>Fulcimentum,</hi> and therefore he formerly hath bene, now is, and euer ſhall be our <hi>Delectamentam.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="4">4 To the Recreement of the whole Land.<milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="4"/> For muſt not the whole Land be much cheered in this his ſafe Returne? Yes, if they would duely conſider the precious woorth that is in him. For, what is he? Euen ſuch a one that if he were to come to his <hi>Throne</hi> by Election, as he is by Succeſsion; doubtleſſe, their votes ſhould be giuen for him: and as the Elders of Iſrael went and ſeized <hi>Iephtah</hi> out of the Land of <hi>Tob,</hi> and ſaid,<note n="q" place="margin">Iudg. 11.<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>
               </note> 
               <hi>Come and be our Captaine:</hi> So he ſhould be ſeized out of what place ſoeuer he remained in, and with the like entreaty, <hi>Ve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ni &amp; eſto nobis Rex, Come and be our King.</hi> What
<pb n="28" facs="tcp:3607:17"/>
Nation would not be glad to haue ſuch a one if it might be to ſit in their throne? He beares in him the Image of a Ruler as <hi>Zebah</hi> and <hi>Sal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>manah</hi> ſaid of the brethren of <hi>Gidion</hi> that they looked like the <hi>Children of a King.</hi>
               <note n="r" place="margin">Iudg. 8.18</note> What can bee deſired in him (ſet aſide a freedome from that naturall, humane, hereditary frailty, that we are all borne with, and ſhall euer bee bur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thened withall) but in ſome meaſure, yea in an eminent degree in him may be eſpied?</p>
            <p>
               <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="1"/> Firſt he is true to our God. The <hi>Feare of I<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſaack is that that he worſhips, from the God of his Fathers will he not depart.</hi> Doubtles of the minde of <hi>Iſchyrion, Sexcenties potius mori quam quicqua<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> de Religione amittere.</hi> That he had rather dye ſixe hundred deaths then loſe the leaſt ſyllable of his profeſsion: his praiſe is in the Goſpell, his Fame ſpread throughout the Chriſtian World for his conſtancy to the Faith hee hath beene brought vp in, no leagues, nor bonds of Affinitie will make him mutable.</p>
            <p>
               <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="2"/> Secondly, He begins to be of a valiant diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſition, continually exerciſing himſelfe in the feates of Armes, and in the times of <hi>Peace</hi> fit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting himſelfe for the times of <hi>War,</hi> ſhewing in his tender yeares good teſtimonies of ſpright<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly courage and puiſſant valour, like to be <q>Marte Ferox, &amp; vincineſcius armis.</q>
            </p>
            <p>
               <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="3"/> Thirdly, He is Prudent. How can it bee o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>therwiſe, when our <hi>Cyrus</hi> hath had ſo many a worthy <hi>Zenophon</hi> to inſtruct him, and he him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelfe
<pb n="29" facs="tcp:3607:17"/>
by Nature taking delight ſcarſe in any thing more then in the companie of the Lear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned and being of the number of them that doe euen —<hi>Impalleſcere chartis,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Perſius.</note> by all ſort of Learning, endeauouring to adapt himſelfe for his Throne, which God in his gratious appoin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted time is like to beſtow vpon him: and as it was a great helpe to <hi>Paul</hi> that he was brought vp at the feet of <hi>Gamaliel,</hi> for his knowledge of the <hi>Phariſaicall</hi> Profeſsion: So doubtleſſe a great helpe for all kind of Knowledge hath it beene to our Prince, to haue bene brought vp at the Feet of ſo ſage and diſcreet a Parent: for who knowes not, that <hi>Jacobus noſter Rex &amp; Magus, Rex &amp; Philoſophus?</hi> Yea the Mirrour of the World concerning Wiſdome, either in Church or State Points. Oh who can imagine then that the Father that deſires to leaue this Sonne the Succeſſor of his King<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>domes and Fame, but he will ouerlay him with the pureſt gold he can, and as he hath commu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nicated to him his humane nature: So like<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wiſe will he endeauour to infuſe into him his intellectuall ſpirit, that he might liue in him when he is dead, and ſhine in his <hi>Sonne</hi> when he is gathered to his <hi>Fathers.</hi> And beſide, hath he trauelled ſo farre onely to ſee Cities, and to embrace Compeeres? No doubtleſſe, that olde <hi>Neſtor</hi> knew well enough what hee did when he parted for a while with his Sonne, he conſidered that by this Voyage hee ſhould
<pb n="30" facs="tcp:3607:18"/>
be much more enabled for Rule and Gouern<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment by his diligent obſeruing and carefull marking of the faſhions, and gouernments of other Nations: So that being by nature ſtu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dious, by education ſo well trained vp, and ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uing beene thus long amongſt the Wits of the World, and the Craftſ-maſters for all ſort of Diſcipline, and Policie, he cannot but haue <hi>Crura thymo plera.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="4"/> Fourthly, he is like to be no ſucker of your veines, nor piller of your profits, but to liue ſo farre as may bee of his owne Royall De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>meanes, accounting that money baſe (as <hi>Ti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>berius</hi> was wont to ſay) that was gotten with the teares and groanes of the people; for hee hath ſhewne himſelfe hither towards of a Princely diſpoſition, and to be no gripple ga<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>therer.</p>
            <p>
               <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="5"/> Fiftly, He is like to be of no haſtie humour, ready to quarrel with his neighbor Princes, or in ſudden moods and ires to ſend challenges of defiance to his adioyning friends, which might make the ſides of his own Kingdome to bleed, yea the heart-ſtrings of Chriſtendome to ake: but he is of a ſtayed carriage, which will enter into no quarrels but vpon mature deliberation and well-pondered reſolution, <q>—Patrem ſequitur ſua Proles.</q>
            </p>
            <p>
               <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="6"/> Sixtly, He is iuſt, not being a Protector of Varlets; for when did he euer bowe his knee, or open his mouth to his Father in a wicked
<pb n="31" facs="tcp:3607:18"/>
mans cauſe? No, he hates them all right ſore, and hath not diſſembled to be their good friend when opportunitie haue bene giuen. And if they haue bene vnder his owne wing, how ſoone hath he chaſed them from him? For how many of his Attendants, if hee haue once per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceiued them to be of any deperdit debauſhed carriage, and in their execrable manners grew incorrigible, how ſoone hath hee diſmiſſed them.</p>
            <p>So now then, <hi>En Principem,</hi> behold your Prince: Oh, how ſhould that people bee euen tranſported that haue receiued by the mercy of God ſuch a Prince out of danger in ſafety; me thinkes their hearts ſhould leape for ioy to heare ſuch tidings of him, and they ſhould goe vp and downe their ſtreets, and with the grea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teſt melody ſound it abroad as their <hi>Paean, Prin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cipem iterum habemus, Principem iterum habe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mus, Wee haue our Prince againe, Wee haue our Prince againe.</hi> The Woods haue not deſtroyed him, the Floods haue not deuoured him, the Ayre hath not infected him, <hi>Principem iterum habemus. Principem iterum habemus. Wee haue our Prince againe, Wee haue our Prince againe.</hi> I read vpon happy euents, many people won<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derfully affected, When <hi>Abraham</hi> had recei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ued that Diuine Promiſe, that <hi>Sarahs</hi> wombe that ſeemed dead ſhould waxe fruitfull, and that ſhee ſhould bee the Mother of many Nati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons, and that Kings ſhould come of her,<note n="ſ" place="margin">Gen. 17.1<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>
               </note> 
               <hi>Hee
<pb n="32" facs="tcp:3607:19"/>
fell on his face and laughed:</hi> And was it not thus with <hi>Iacob?</hi> Yes, when newes was brought him that <hi>Ioſeph,</hi> whom he thought long before to haue beene torne in peices by a wild beaſt, to bee yet aliue, and by the Chariots that were ſent hee plainly perceiued it.<note n="t" place="margin">Gen. 45.27 21, v.</note>
               <hi>The ſpirit of Iacob reuiued, and hee ſaid, I haue inough, Io<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeph my ſonne is yet aliue.</hi> And were not the Iewes in this degree of exceſſiue gladſomneſſe? Yes, for wh<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>n <hi>Mordecai</hi> was exalted, and the cruell Edict of <hi>Haman</hi> reuerſed, and comforta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble letters ſent in the ſtead<note n="u" place="margin">Eſt. 8.</note> 
               <hi>All the City of Shuſham reioyced, and there was ioy and glad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>n<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ſſe, a Feaſt and a good day.</hi> And ſhall wee not finde <hi>Rhoda,</hi> and the Saints of God at <hi>Peters</hi> miraculous deliuerance out of Priſon, iuſt in this caſe? Yes, <hi>Rhoda</hi> hearing him knocke at the doore, and by his voyce knowing it to bee him<note n="w" place="margin">Acts 12.14, 16.</note> 
               <hi>Opened not the doore for very gladneſſe,</hi> and when the Saints ſaw him, <hi>they were aſtonied.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>And not only in the Sacred Scriptures, but in Sacred Hiſtories this extraordinary ioy we doe finde vpon extraordinary euents.<note n="x" place="margin">Euſeb. P<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>p. Hiſt. lib. <hi>9.</hi> c. <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>.</note> 
               <hi>Euſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bius</hi> reports, that when <hi>Maximius</hi> the Eaſterne Tyrant had ſent commandement to his Preſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dents, that the Chriſtians which were perſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cut<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>d ſhould be releaſed, that the noble Cham<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pions of godlineſſe which before were in the Mine-pits, paſſed through euery City with valiant and cheerfull courage, with vnſpeaka<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble ioy, and repleniſhed with inexplicable li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>berty
<pb n="33" facs="tcp:3607:19"/>
of minde, and that they ſung Songs and Pſalmes in the midde high-wayes, in the mar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ket places, and all frequented Aſſemblies.<note n="y" place="margin">Euſeb. ibid. c. <hi>9.</hi>
               </note> In like manner it is reported that <hi>Conſtantine</hi> ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uing conquered <hi>Maxentius</hi> that truculent oppreſſour comming to Rome, immediately with cheerefull countenance, and from the heart hee was receiued of all both Men, Wo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>men and Children, Senators, and other Noble Perſonages, &amp; of all the People of Rome with gladſome ſhouts, and vnſpeakable ioy, as a Deliuerer from opppreſſion, and generall Be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nefactor to all.<note n="z" place="margin">Socrates Scholaſt Ecc. Hiſt. lib. <hi>7.</hi> c. <hi>23.</hi>
               </note> So likewiſe when by the Prayers of <hi>Theodoſius</hi> that vertuous Emperour the vſurping Tyrant <hi>Iohn</hi> was brought to his end by valiant <hi>Aſpar,</hi> all the people ſet all at nought, and paſſed the Theatre, (where before they were celebrating their ſhowes and ſpec<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tacles <hi>in Circo</hi>) ſounding out thankſ-giuing together with the Emperour with one voyce, and ſtraitway went to Church, and ſpent there the whole day: ſo that all the City ſeemed to bee but as one Church. And not onely in ſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cred Scriptures and in ſacred Hiſtories, but among the Heathens vpon occaſions of happy betides, much expreſſion of ioy haue beene manifeſted. It is reported that when the people of Rome heard how <hi>Germanicus</hi> (whoſe life and welfare they much feared) was in ſafe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty; as if they had beene ouercome with the newes, they went and rent open their Tem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple
<pb n="34" facs="tcp:3607:20"/>
dores, and cryed out, <hi>Salua Patria, Salua Ci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uitas, ſaluus Germanicus. Our Country is ſafe, our Citty is ſafe, Germanicus is ſafe.</hi> And of <hi>Cicero</hi> wee read, that returning from baniſh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment in the Conſulſhips of <hi>Pompey</hi> and <hi>Len<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tulus,</hi> that <hi>Tanta fuit vrbis laetitia, vt (quaſi a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uulſa ſedibus ſuis Roma) omnis aetas ordoſ<expan>
                     <am>
                        <g ref="char:abque"/>
                     </am>
                     <ex>que</ex>
                  </expan> homi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>num obuiam procederet. That there was ſuch re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ioycing in the City, that Rome was as it were ſha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ken and plucked from her ſeate, all ages and orders of men going out to meet Cicero.</hi> What ſhould I ſeeke to abound? The drift of my ſpeech is, that as it is naturall to all men with memora<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble chances to bee delighted, ſo wee for this late fauour of God vouchſafed vnto vs ſhould bee, <hi>ſupra modum dulcedine laeti.</hi> fraught and repleniſhed with ioy beyond mea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſure, euen fall on our faces and laugh, haue our Spirits reuiued within vs, haue amongſt vs a feaſt and a good day, yea in the higheſt man<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ner we can expreſſe our Iubiliation and ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ultation? Oh they haue dead hearts that are not now quickened, dumbe mouthes that doe not now ſound forth ioyfull out cries: if euer there were a time for the Timbrell and the dance, this is it, the returne of our Prince into the Land ſhould bee like returne of life into a ſwounding body; wee ſhould haue as much gladneſſe for the hauing of him, as wee ſhould haue had ſadneſſe for the wanting of him; if hee had periſhed, how ſhould wee haue mour<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned?
<pb n="35" facs="tcp:3607:20"/>
being preſerued, and in all ſort of peace returned, how ſhould wee triumph? our ioy ſhould be like the ioy of Harueſt; yea men that are diuiding ſpoyles ſhould not bee more cheerefull then wee: Our Sauiour ſaith in the Goſpell <hi>If theſe ſhould hold their peace, the ſtones would ſpeake;</hi> ſo if wee ſhould not re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ioyce, the ſenſleſſe Starres would teach vs ioy.</p>
            <p>Our Prince went out with a wonder, and came home with a wonder: out with a won<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der; for the Thames your Channell, many o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther places in the Land ſtrangely ebbed and flowed, as if the waters had been out of courſe, that a Prince of ſuch matchleſſe worth ſhould be wafted ere long ouer them to paſſe through many dangers: came home with a wonder, for being paſt all his dreads, and arriued again vpon his owne ſhoares, the fame of his re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>turne being ſcarſe ſpread throughout all the parts of this Kingdome; yea the very day the tidings came amongſt you, the two great Lights of Heauen in an aſtoniſhable manner appeared, there being three Moones in the night, three Sunnes in the Morning, to ſigni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fie vnto vs that the Heyre apparant (if my coniecture bee not too curious) of three Kingdoms was now in ſafety rerurned, yea that the <hi>Lord our Prince was come home in peace.</hi> Therefore as <hi>Salomon</hi> ſaith, <hi>Goe to the Piſmire O thou Sluggard;</hi> ſo goe to the Lights of Hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uen
<pb n="36" facs="tcp:3607:21"/>
and lighten thee vnto ioy, O thou dull-hearted Subiect.</p>
            <p>But I muſt needs confeſſe I need not bee ouermuch vehement for this duty in this place. Fot as the Woman from the wall com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mended the City of <hi>Abel,</hi> that it was <hi>a faith<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full and peaceable Daughter in Iſrael:</hi> ſo for this I may ſafely commend you, that you haue ſhowne your ſelues full of ardent loue and ſur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>paſſing ioy; yea, as <hi>Jacob</hi> ſaid of <hi>LuZ</hi> in re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpect of the diuine Viſion of the Ladder, which reached vp to the Heauen, and the Angels a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcended and deſcended vpon it, that it was no other but the <hi>Houſe of God, and the Gate of Heauen:</hi> So, hauing beheld the Ladder of your ioy reaching as it were with the excelſe and ſublime exultations to the height of Heauen, and yourſ<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>lues aſcending and deſcending vpon it, I cannot but acknowledge, that this is no other but a Port where the King and Prince haue true-hearted &amp; free-hearted obeiſants. Who that did but ſee or ſhall but heare of the number of people that heere was met once before and now againe, ſuch a maruellous Congregation, as if your Houſes were emptyed to fill the Houſe of God, and beſides your Church-ioy, your Streets-melody, your Inſtruments of Muſicke, your Banners diſplayed, your Ordnance roaring, your Bonefires flaming, but muſt needs confeſſe that yee haue beene very forward to giue vnto this ſucceſsfull, proſperous, long-wiſhed for be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tide
<pb n="37" facs="tcp:3607:21"/>
due ſolemnity? <hi>Many Daughters haue done worthily, but thou ſurmounteſt all;</hi> All, con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſidering the bigneſſe or rather ſmalneſſe of the Towne: Many of your aged Fathers, with countenances aſtoniſhed, and with droppes of ioy trickling along their cheekes, acknowledg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing that ſuch triumphing they did neuer behold: Well, your workes ſhall praiſe you in the Gates, your egregious acts gaine you Illuſtrious Fame, they ſhall make your friends to extoll you, your enemies to admire you, and both friends and enemies in all your wants ready to relieue you. Goe on therefore thus loyally and affectionate<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly to celebrate the returne of him, who came from Strangers Borders with honour, and who ought to be receiued into our Coaſts with ra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uiſhment.</p>
            <p>But wil ſome ſay <hi>Corda tremunt, Interiora qua<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiunt,</hi> our hearts tre<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ble, our inwards ſhake with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>in vs, we cannot bee ioyfull as we would, becauſe though our Prince be come home in peace; yet we ſhal neuer be in long peace vnder him; for a Spaniſh Match will come, and then the Papiſts they feare may draw him from his Religion. <hi>Curſe not the King, no not in thy thoughts;</hi> ſo curſe not the Prince in thy priuate conceits, coniectures. Hee hath deſerued the beſt opi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nion and worthieſt eſtimation of vs. Hath he beene conſtant to the faith in <hi>Spaine,</hi> and will hee heere bee a Reed ſhaken with the winde? Did he there ſo ſtoutly ſtand, and will he heere
<pb n="38" facs="tcp:3607:22"/>
ſo readily fall? No doubtleſſe, the heart of our Prince is more confirmed againſt the Ro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſh Church then before; the ſight of their Abominations haue bred in him greater de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teſtation. And howſoeuer the King for ſome ouertures to vs vndiſcloſed, may purpoſe, yea proſecute the Match; yet the heart of the King, as <hi>Salomon</hi> ſaith is deepe, wee cannot ſearch it, he hath ſome high and deepe Proiect in hand; but harmeleſſe, no doubt, is his inten<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion to vs; and perſwade your ſelues both King and Prince know the <hi>Beaſt</hi> and his <hi>Lo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cuſts</hi> well enough; they will take heed of bowing their necke vnder that heauy vnſup<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>portable Yoake, the miſerable examples of their Predeceſſors, their Neighbours, their ſelues, cannot out of their hearts: therefore though ſo farre as wee through our darke cre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uiſes can diſcerne, could wiſh matters might goe otherwiſe, and we would giue the eyes in our heads to obtaine it; yet becauſe we ſee but the outſide of things, and the inward ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>crets wee cannot ranſacke, nor pry into, there being ſuch wiſe Pilots at the Sterne, let vs commit all vnto them with quietneſſe, truſting that they will not ſuffer the ſhippe to miſcary. And therefore let this ſtone of offence bee re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>moued, let vs not bee troubled with any feares of great miſeries enſuing; wee are like to ſit vnder our owne Vines, and our owne Figge-trees in peace, and therefore let vs confidently
<pb n="39" facs="tcp:3607:22"/>
and intrepidly goe on to be ioyed; yea euen ouer-ioyed with the enioying of that Iewell which a while wee wanted, for this let our hearts be enflamed, our ſpirits filled with mar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uellous iucundity; yea let vs euen know no meaſure nor moderation in the comfort that wee take in the ſame, beſide a little, let vs en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deauour to track <hi>Mephiboſheths</hi> ſteps in for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>giuing, and giuing.</p>
            <p>Firſt in forgiuing; for as hee forgaue <hi>Zibah,</hi> ſo let vs forgiue: 1. Our enemies. 2. Our Debtors.</p>
            <p>Our Enemies: For how vnſightly a thing would it be that they w<hi rend="sup">t</hi> come to reioyce at the ſame Temple, and which goe triumphing in the ſame Streets, ſhould looke with euill aſpects, like Malignant Planets, one vpon another? Where there is ioynt Reioycing<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> there ſhould bee ioynt Reconcilement; Oh how acceptable would it be to the Lord, our Prince if hee might be wel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>commed home with the Nobles and Commons, laying downe all their priuate ſpleenenes? They could not bee more ioyfull to ſee him in Peace from Dangers; then hee to ſee them in Peace from Grudges: their hearty concord would with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out all queſtion be his hearty conſolation; but if their eyes looke cheerefully vpon him, but are ready to looke aſquint one vpon another, and their mouthes ſhoot in ioy of his Returne, but are ready to glow with Rage, and to ſpew out ſcandals, ignominies, opprobrious, calumnious
<pb n="40" facs="tcp:3607:23"/>
ſpeeches one againſt annother; if they clap their hands in his honour, but ready to ſmite with the fiſt of wickedneſſe, as the Prophet ſaith, or to ſtrike their hands in token of indignation as <hi>Balack</hi> did againſt <hi>Balaam:</hi> How great a a quenching will this be to the Lord our Prince, for that true full ioy he ſhould take in the Peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ples Melody-makings? Oh therefore let all bit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter rootes be plucked vp, all old greeuances re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>moued, all indignities, abuſes forgiuen, be <hi>Me<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phiboſheths.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Our Debtours: For, can we truely reioyce in our Princes Returne, and yet ſuffer others to mourne in the Houſe of Bondage? Is their meanes waſted, their Eſtates ſo decayed, that they are not able to ſatisfie, and yet will yee ſuf<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fer them in Priſon, rather to pine away then yeeld to releaſe them? oh remember this is not a time with all rigour and extremitie to exact debts; therefore now let vs eaſe burthens, free enthralled men, and giue them liberty vpon this gladſome tydings.</p>
            <p>Secondly, in giuing, and that towards the Poore, and Prince.</p>
            <p>Firſt, towards the Poore. For vpon this oc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>caſion ſhould not rich mens houſes bee like the Courts of <hi>Charitie?</hi> Yes, for a <hi>Nabal</hi> hee is in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deed, that now eats his bread &amp; his fleſh onely a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mongſt his <hi>Sheepe-ſhearers,</hi> therefore bring forth the raiment for the naked, the ſiluer for the nee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dy, the ſuſtenance for the hungry &amp; thirſty, giue
<pb n="41" facs="tcp:3607:23"/>
Portions to ſeuen and likewiſe to eight.</p>
            <p>To the Prince. For this voyage muſt needs haue bene coſtly and chargeable. Princes whenſoeuer they trauell muſt be Liberall to honour the State from whence they come: and ſhould not theſe ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pences be made vp by vs? Yes, whenſoeuer he cal we ſhould haue our preſents ready; for will wee beſtow nothing but a little ſounding of Cornets, and Sackbuts, Powder and ſhot, Bonefires and ringing of Bells? This were poore congratulati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, cheape welcome. Let our Coffers therefore be opened, our Eſtates ſet forth, and ſeeing the <hi>Lord our Prince is come home in Peace</hi> let him take am<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ply, freely.</p>
            <p>But amongſt all theſe Solemnities, let vs not forget the Fat of the Peace offering. How came the Lord our Prince thus home in Peace, but by the Prouidence of God? <hi>Giue vnto God therefore that which is Gods, Let him take</hi> 1. <hi>Preſent De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uotion.</hi> 2. <hi>Future Dutie.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Firſt, Preſent Deuotion. For, <hi>Bring vnto the Lord oh ye Sons of the Mightie, bring young Rammes vnto the Lord, aſcribe vnto the Lord the honour due to his Name. Come into his Courts with Thankeſ-gi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uing, and ſhew your ſelues glad in him with Pſalmes.</hi> Let not ſo precious a benefit be receiued without praiſe, nor ſo Gracious a Fauour without con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>digne commemoration. <hi>It becommeth well the Iuſt to be thankfull.</hi> Let his name be extolled, his mercy magnified.</p>
            <p>Secondly, Future Dutie. For hath not God try<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed
<pb n="42" facs="tcp:3607:24"/>
by his fauours to Winne vs, by his bleſsings to drawe vs vnto him? Yes, the Lord might haue paid vs home at one ſtroake, but he hath ſpared vs, to ſee if we will open our eyes and ſee his good<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe, open our eares and heare his will, open our hearts and follow his precepts; Oh therefore with the Cords of his loue let vs be pulled vnto him, let this vnſpeakeable fauour bring vs vnto vnfeyned duty: Yea, <hi>Seeing the Lord our Prince is come home in Peace, let him take All.</hi> All Seruice both of Body and Soule.</p>
            <p>By this time I truſt I haue taught you how your Cup might runne ouer with the oyle of gladneſſe, and how you might rightly and fully diſcharge what belongs to you vpon this bleſſed Euent.</p>
            <p>What laſt ſhall be done? Let vs ſet our mouthes toward Heauen, &amp; implore Diuine aſſiſtance for after times for our Prince. The Lord water him with y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> dew of Heaue<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, endew him with his further graces, cauſe his face ſtil to ſhine vpo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> him, his mer<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>cies ſtill to keepe him, his Spirit ſtil to direct him, that our ioyes may abound vnder him, our happi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe encreaſe as his yeares encreaſe, that if this worthy Prince ſuruiue that matchleſſe Father, as now we receiue him with Triumph into the Land, ſo then we may receiue him with Triumph into his Throne, and at laſt hee may bee receiued by the Angels, and Archangels with Honour and Glory into Heauen. <hi>Amen.</hi>
            </p>
            <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
